<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: smartphones | Practical Elegance]]></title>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/categories/smartphones/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-11T22:58:41-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://decomplecting.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lewis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goodbye AT&amp;T, Hello T-Mobile?]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/12/23/goodbye-at-and-t/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T21:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/12/23/goodbye-at-and-t</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I&rsquo;m curious about this <a href="http://guardianlv.com/2013/12/t-mobile-uncarrier-4-0-reportedly-will-buyout-contracts-when-switching/">Uncarrier 4.0</a> thing rumoured to be rolled out by <a href="http://www.t-mobile.com/">T-Mobile</a> in the near future&hellip; I&rsquo;ve considered ditching <a href="http://www.att.com/shop/wireless.html">AT&amp;T Wireless</a> many times, but keep getting dragged back in by upgrades, which seem to take longer and longer to happen.</p>

<p>I tried to get my wife an upgrade for Christmas this year, just to find out <em>both</em> our upgrade dates are far, far in the future&hellip; I&rsquo;m pretty certain we got more frequent upgrades a while back, but the current cycle seems absurd. I was fine with early contract renewals when it meant I got a shiny new phone, but when your renewal date is the same as your upgrade date (24 months), they&rsquo;ve removed all incentive not to switch carriers. Which inidcates to me that perhaps their wireless division is run by idiots, indicating an incentive <em>to</em> switch carriers.</p>

<p>The last counter-incentive to switching is the Early Termination Fee, which, when you&rsquo;re on a family plan and have multiple phones out-of-sync on contract renewal dates, is a bitch to work around. Now, for my part, I&rsquo;m a committed Nexus fan, so I&rsquo;m on an unsubsidised phone anyhow. But with T-Mobile, I can get my Nexus 5 straight from the carrier, Candice can pick out the phone she likes, and we can get more frequent upgrades without a contract.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So the real question is, what&rsquo;s the downside?</p>

<p>Well, AT&amp;T does have better overall coverage (and definitely better LTE coverage) than T-Mobile&hellip; for now. But we rarely leave Baltimore except to visit family, and all of the places we do visit family have excellent voice coverage, and we&rsquo;ll be on WiFi at their houses, so&hellip; I&rsquo;m really considering it.</p>

<p>If anyone has made the jump, please let me know in the comments. As soon as T-Mobile rolls out this &ldquo;we&rsquo;ll buy out your contract&rdquo; deal, I&rsquo;m probably ready to jump ship. I&rsquo;ve never had any great love for AT&amp;T, and waiting <em>two years</em> for an upgrade is just stupid. Hell, even getting out of carrier lock-in would be nice, and access to Deutsche Telekom&rsquo;s global data network would be gravy if we start traveling as much as we&rsquo;d like.</p>

<p>Anyhow&hellip; just ruminations for the moment, but&hellip; it could be pretty great.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
