<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Practical Elegance]]></title>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-22T23:11:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://decomplecting.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lewis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In Memoriam: Wolfgang Walter Fuchs]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/12/22/in-memoriam-wolfgang-walter-fuchs/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T22:05:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/12/22/in-memoriam-wolfgang-walter-fuchs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was recently corresponding with a professor of mine about Wittgenstein, planning to set up a meeting to have a chat and catch up. Oh, and talk about Wittgenstein, as I found another place where philosophy is relevant to programming. In my last email to him, I happened to ask after one of his colleagues, who was my advisor, mentor, and one of the most influential people in my life.</p>

<p>Then I remembered Google, and the first result was <a href="http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2014-03-01/news/bs-md-ob-walt-fuchs-20140228_1_towson-university-philosophy-liberal-arts-building">an obituary</a>.</p>

<p>I was devastated. Indescribably so. Biblicallly devastated; I literally rent my garments in grief. I really liked that shirt, too.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is Dr. Fuchs:</p>

<p><img src="/images/post-img/walt-fuchs.jpg" title="Walter Fuchs" ></p>

<p>Dr. Fuchs helped lay the groundwork for my life in more ways than he probably ever knew, and I am eternally grateful for the privilege of knowing him. In the same conversation, I think he convinced me that I would make an excellent professor of philosophy and proceeded to convince me not to pursue that path.</p>

<p>He was such an odd bird. He was never seen without a black leather vest, and practiced Tae Kwon Do in the hallway between classes.</p>

<p>One interesting thing, from this weekend while I was in the darkest part of mourning. I happened to post an aphorism from Nietzsche which (reasonably) concerned my friends and family:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>“The thought of suicide is a powerful solace: by means of it one gets through many a bad night”</p><footer><strong>Friedrich Nietzsche</strong> <cite>Beyond Good and Evil</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I later explained the context, I&rsquo;ll just repost the comment:</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>I think I chose that aphorism because Dr. Fuchs helped me to understand it; Nietzsche&rsquo;s philosophy was about embracing life, and the thought that it could be easily ended, by one&rsquo;s own hand, should serve to remind us that however bad things were, if one hadn&rsquo;t done so, one had already chosen to plough through and endure.</p></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>

<p>What else can I say about the man&hellip;</p>

<p>Unlike some professors, he would never use his own (expensive, thanks to academic publishers) texts to teach his classes. His own essay (based on his Ph.D. thesis) <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Phenomenology-Metaphysics-Presence-Philosophy-Phaenomenologica/dp/9024718228"><em>Phenomenology and The Metaphysics of Presence</em></a> would never be required (or even suggested) for his courses, although that book is how I really came to understand Husserl and the thread connecting him to Derrida.</p>

<p>It was kind of a blow and kind of a breath of fresh air that after all the classes where I had to buy the professor&rsquo;s shite book, the one book that was really helpful wasn&rsquo;t on the reading list on ethical grounds.</p>

<p>I think much of my sorrow comes from the fact that I did such a shite job of staying in touch over the years. It&rsquo;s been over a decade since we spoke. I have a lot of regret to get over due to this.</p>

<p>I had a fucked up weekend, drinking and crying and listening to The Smiths.</p>

<p>Someone asked me, &ldquo;would he want you to mourn like this?&rdquo;</p>

<p>And it reminded me of a conversation we had.</p>

<p>I expressed some reservations one time over Sartre&rsquo;s adopted daughter publishing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Truth-Existence-Jean-Paul-Sartre/dp/0226735230/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1419305694&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=truth+and+existence"><em>Truth and Existence</em></a> after his death and against his wishes.</p>

<p>And Dr. Fuchs pointed out that Sartre would likely have considered it ungenerous to have designs beyond one&rsquo;s own death. Certainly Heidegger, asserting the finality of death as the <em>sine qua non</em> for a meaningful existence, would not attempt to subvert that finality.</p>

<p>Death is good. Death is what makes us mortal, makes us human, gives us meaning. Without death, life would have no size.</p>

<p>And we know this, yet we sigh, and weep, and allow our sorrow to drive us.</p>

<p>But human life is finite, and perhaps the Stoics teach us the best lesson: how to die well.</p>

<p>I hope Dr. Fuchs had a good death. I&rsquo;m certain he had a full and vibrant life.</p>

<p>Let us celebrate his life, and mourn our loss, but not his death, for he has completed his journey. He has achieved that end which ensures the meaning of his life.</p>

<p>Good journey, Dr. Fuchs. I will always love and miss you. Thank you for the light you shone into my life, and may you pass well into whatever lies beyond this fragile existence.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elegant Organizations]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2012/05/29/elegant-organizations/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-29T20:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2012/05/29/elegant-organizations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a long time, Jason Fried&rsquo;s article <a href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20110401/jason-fried-why-i-run-a-flat-company.html">Why I Run a Flat Company</a> has seemed like an unrealistic dream that only works in rarified pockets of hacker utopia.</p>

<p>You have to understand, I work for an institution which, between the university, hospital(s), and various other divisions, employs over 40k people, enrolls over 20k students, treats countless patients, and who knows how many vendors and contractors add complexity to the mix.</p>

<p>But I still think there&rsquo;s something to this &ldquo;flat company&rdquo; idea. My team is a bit of an oddity, and I think that&rsquo;s what allows us to be agile and innovative in a way that&rsquo;s impossible for most of the other software teams. The team is, on an org chart, pretty much flat. We have a team lead, to whom we <em>don&rsquo;t</em> report (on paper).</p>

<p>Let me backtrack a bit. In interest of full disclosure, I do have a bit of a cognitive bias in favor of flat organizations. My lefty politics tend toward anarchist-communism, so I have a certain degree of distrust for <em>any</em> hierarchy. I think this goes back to the important distinction between <em>having</em> authority and <em>being an</em> authority. The difference between a bestowed, arbitrary power, and the innate power of being intelligent, capable, and well-informed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>From this perspective, the (practical) ideal would be a democratically-managed, worker-owned organization where salaries/wages were ditched in favor of profit sharing.</p>

<p>I think software is one business where this ideal is eminently practicable; but let me get back to &ldquo;the real world.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Specifically, my job.</p>

<p>On an org chart, it goes CIO &ndash;> Sr. Director &ndash;> Director &ndash;> me. Let me note <em>this is weird</em> for my organization. Normally, it would be something like CIO &ndash;> Sr. Director &ndash;> Director &ndash;> IT Manager &ndash;> IT Architect &ndash;> Señor Software Engineer &ndash;> Software Engineer &ndash;> Señor Programmer Analyst (me) and there would likely be some kind of &ldquo;Peasant Programmer Analyst&rdquo; for whom I was responsible. I won&rsquo;t go into the fact that if I wrote out what I actually do, it would be 2-3 levels above my pay grade (well, at least not yet).</p>

<p>My team creates enhancements for legacy systems that makes jaws drop among senior VPs from the company that sold us these systems. It&rsquo;s super cool, and after our public release this summer, I&rsquo;ll be able to talk about them. And beleive me, I will. I&rsquo;m super-proud of this stuff.</p>

<p>But the question remains, how is it we pull this stuff off with 1.4 developers, one sysadmin/network engineer/informal team lead, and one hardware/support guy?</p>

<p>I think the lack of formal management is key. Our director is fairly hands-off, as long as we&rsquo;re meeting goals and keeping the customers satisfied (which we nearly always are). Our team lead recognizes where the real expertise is among the team, and defers to the judgment of the de facto &ldquo;experts&rdquo; where appropriate. We are a flat team in an eminently hierarchical organization. And we kick ass.</p>

<p>Recently, our audacious innovation has come onto the radar of the CIO and senior IT management team (among others). That&rsquo;s pretty damn cool, on the one hand. On the other, by being <em>off</em> the radar, we&rsquo;ve managed to create this cohesive little unit that actually <em>works.</em> We&rsquo;ve also been able to choose a stack based on what will pull off the impossible in a timely fashion, rather than what our approved vendors provide.</p>

<p>We run <a href="http://debian.org">Debian</a> on most of our production servers. Our web apps are built with <a href="http://rubyonrails.org">Ruby on Rails</a>, and there&rsquo;s some <a href="http://jruby.org">JRuby</a> and <a href="http://clojure.org">Clojure</a> stuff in the works.</p>

<p>This is unheard of. This in a place where Windows Server is the default, where ASP.NET is the preferred web technology&hellip;</p>

<p>I think the problem with having layers and layers of management is that managers need to look like they&rsquo;re <em>doing</em> something. Usually, this invovles purchasing decisions, standards impostion, and adding more layers of inefficient management.</p>

<p>When you have a relatively flat organization, it&rsquo;s more important to hire smart people who can generally handle themselves, set the mat a task, and be ready to support them as necessary. That&rsquo;s how we work, and the result speaks for itself.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>We&rsquo;ve experimented with promoting a few people to manager-level roles. In some cases, this has worked out; in others, it hasn&rsquo;t. But one thing we&rsquo;ve found is that groups that manage themselves are often better off than groups that are managed by a single person. So when groups do require structure, we get them to manage themselves.</p><footer><strong>Jason Fried</strong> <cite><a href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20110401/jason-fried-why-i-run-a-flat-company.html">http://www.inc.com/magazine/20110401/jason-fried-why-i-run-a-flat-company.html</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Of course, innovation isn&rsquo;t <em>always</em> the top priority. But I think whenever possible, it should be towards the very top of the list. Innovation is the key to competitiveness, and whether you&rsquo;re a university, a hospital, or a software company, ultimately it comes down to the bottom line: how do we increase revenues and decrease expenditures?</p>

<p>Creating innovative features that can attract new customers, and save work for staff, at the same time, ultimately mean that deep down, you&rsquo;re a profit center, even if you&rsquo;re still classified by the dreaded beancounters as a cost center. And in this crazy, mixed-up world, that&rsquo;s what it&rsquo;s all about.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
