<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: management | Practical Elegance]]></title>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/categories/management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-29T02:29:35-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://decomplecting.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lewis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Myth of The "IT Department"]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/03/15/the-myth-of-the-it-department/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/03/15/the-myth-of-the-it-department</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So in the comments on my <a href="/blog/2013/03/11/confessions-of-a-job-destroyer/">last post</a> I mentioned my fandom
for what is, in my opinion, the most insightful and important blog currently
published, that of <a href="http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/">Michael O. Church</a>.
His recent series of posts have been reviewing and analyzing the MacLeod theory
of <a href="http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/gervais-macleod-9-convexity/">organizational structure</a>
(link is to the latest post in the series, but if you haven&rsquo;t been following it,
therein are links to the previous eight).</p>

<p>I want to focus on the differential between concave (in which the difference
between failure and middling is greatest) and convex (in which the difference
between middling and superior is greatest) work.</p>

<h3>The &ldquo;IT Department&rdquo;</h3>

<p>I have to start by saying &ldquo;Information Technology&rdquo; is a leaky abstraction. It
covers everything from internal software development to the help desk call
center. I&rsquo;m not suggesting that either line of business is superior. Both are
absolutely necessary, at least until developers start to become psychic or users
stop being stupid, or (preferably) both.</p>

<p>The real problem comes when the same management structure is imposed in the
guise of an &ldquo;IT Department&rdquo; on such divergent areas as the help desk, desktop
support, network engineers, developers, and hardware techs. Going beyond
theories <a href="http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2013/03/12/gervais-macleod-8-human-nature-theories-x-y-z-and-a/">X, Y, Z, or A</a>
of management, having a &ldquo;Central IT&rdquo; department is (without a revolutionary
management strategy that will probably raise HR issues for most entrenched
organizations) an attempt to shoehorn concave and convex work into the same tiny
box, and is going to fail at appropriately managing one or the other (or perhaps
more likely, both).</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Concave Work</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s face it, help desk work is typically concave. I&rsquo;ve done it (briefly), and
it&rsquo;s probably an acceptable use case for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_X_and_Theory_Y#Theory_X">Theory X</a>, since it&rsquo;s (in
this writer&rsquo;s opinion) rote, unrewarding work that I would
<a href="/blog/2013/03/11/confessions-of-a-job-destroyer/">automate out of existence</a> if I had the time
and resources. But, it&rsquo;s also necessary work, and a place where &ldquo;managing to the
middle&rdquo; works because achieving the Socially Acceptable Middling Effort (SAME)
is a decent departmental average.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d place much of the responsibility of the average sub-division of IT in the
scope of &ldquo;concave work.&rdquo;  Desktop support, Windows administration, etc., are
really about uniformity of outcome, and SAME is an acceptable goal.</p>

<p>When it comes to efforts like software development, or big data, or even &ldquo;cloud
services&rdquo;, SAME is the same as failure. We&rsquo;re now into the realm of convex work,
and the standard has to be different.</p>

<h3>Convex Work</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/blog/2012/10/31/feedback-loops/">written before</a> about how programmers
are just <em>weird</em> from a standard, organizational point of view. Or any standard
point of view. Programming is the ultimate convex work; from Joel Spolsky&rsquo;s
warnings about
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/ThePerilsofJavaSchools.html">The Perils of Java Schools</a>, to
Jeff Atwood&rsquo;s plea that <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/05/please-dont-learn-to-code.html">not everyone learn to code</a>,
it&rsquo;s clear that not only is programming a highly specialized thing to excel at,
but also that there are <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2006/07/separating-programming-sheep-from-non-programming-goats.html">certain factors that determine capability in advance</a>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s probably the epitome of convex work. The difference between the worst
programmer and the middling programmer is a fraction of the difference between a
middling programmer and (even) a 90th percentile-or-above programmer. And there
are probably other areas in IT where this is true; from my experience I&rsquo;d say
they&rsquo;re in software-heavy areas like managing large datasets properly, or
providing true &ldquo;cloud services&rdquo;, i.e., computing and storage in a multi-tenancy
environment with computation and storage as a metered service. I haven&rsquo;t seen
any of these done well in an &ldquo;enterprise&rdquo; environment.</p>

<h3>The Enterprise</h3>

<p>The &ldquo;enterprise&rdquo; only works by &ldquo;managing to the middle.&rdquo; Which explains the
self-defeating attitudes of vendor lock-in and risk aversion. When you&rsquo;re not
in a &ldquo;tech company,&rdquo; IT is invariably a &ldquo;cost center,&rdquo; which a) is why
<a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2011/10/28/dont-call-yourself-a-programmer/">you shouldn&rsquo;t call yourself a programmer</a>
(obligatory reference), and b) why it needs to maintain a low-risk profile. When
you work for a large organization, &ldquo;low-risk&rdquo; means &ldquo;the buck stops elsewhere
than my desk.&rdquo;  So there needs to be a vendor to blame. So much of the
acknowledged efforts will be in contract negotiations for the purchase of
almost-suitable software from an established vendor, that doesn&rsquo;t really meet
the needs of the organization, but can be marginally tweaked to fit by middling
engineers.</p>

<p>It also means that internal innovation can&rsquo;t be acknowledged or rewarded too
highly. When most of your &ldquo;software teams&rdquo; are doing maintenance on the last
failed vendor purchase, how can you be seen to give accolades to the projects
which have truly broken new ground?</p>

<p>At the same time, do you <em>want</em> front line support innovating to that degree?
Sure, if one of your help desk reps replaces some annoying customer interaction
with a Perl script, they&rsquo;ll either be promoted to convex work, or fired from
concave work, right? I think this only reinforces the difference between the two
categories.</p>

<h3>Programmer, Wat Do?</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s where the <a href="http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2013/02/19/gervais-principle-questioned-macleods-hierarchy-the-technocrat-and-vc-startups/">MacLeod Paradigm</a>
really comes into play again&hellip; when most of your developers are 9-to-5ers who
<a href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2012/05/22/passion/">take no joy in their craft</a>,
you have a team of MacLeod &ldquo;losers,&rdquo; which fits perfectly well into the
&ldquo;enterprise&rdquo; IT paradigm. It&rsquo;s hard to practice something sensible like
<a href="http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2012/11/25/programmer-autonomy-is-a-1-trillion-issue/">open allocation</a>
when you manage business analysts in the same manner as developers.</p>

<p>If you really care about good, clean, beautiful, (even) elegant code, well&hellip;
you might luck out. I&rsquo;m on a small team which is probably considered &ldquo;rogue&rdquo; by
most &ldquo;enterprise&rdquo; standards. I love my job, and it affords me significant
autonomy and creative freedom, but I also know how bizarre and rare that is. I
don&rsquo;t see how &ldquo;non-technical organizations&rdquo; (a future post will debate whether
such a thing exists anymore) can afford to treat developers&#8217; work the same as
concave work without having the whole house of cards come tumbling down at some
point.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
