<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: philosophy | Practical Elegance]]></title>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/categories/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T01:50:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://decomplecting.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lewis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Angel of History]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/11/30/the-angel-of-history/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-30T00:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/11/30/the-angel-of-history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It all started with a Paul Klee print, or perhaps that&rsquo;s where it ended:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/post-img/angelus_novus.jpg" title="Angelus Novus" ></p>

<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt_School">Frankfurt School</a> philosopher <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Benjamin">Walter Benjamin</a> owned this print for many years, and one of his most well-know quotations from <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/benjamin/1940/history.htm">&ldquo;On The Concept of History&rdquo;</a> (also known as &ldquo;Theses on The Philosophy of History&rdquo;) is inspired by this painting.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From Thesis IX:</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>There is a painting by Klee called Angelus Novus. An angel is depicted there who looks as though he were about to distance himself from something which he is staring at. His eyes are opened wide, his mouth stands open and his wings are outstretched. The Angel of History must look just so. His face is turned towards the past. Where we see the appearance of a chain of events, he sees one single catastrophe, which unceasingly piles rubble on top of rubble and hurls it before his feet. He would like to pause for a moment so fair [verweilen: a reference to Goethe’s Faust], to awaken the dead and to piece together what has been smashed. But a storm is blowing from Paradise, it has caught itself up in his wings and is so strong that the Angel can no longer close them. The storm drives him irresistibly into the future, to which his back is turned, while the rubble-heap before him grows sky-high. That which we call progress, is this storm.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Walter Benjamin</strong> <cite>&ldquo;On the Concept of History&rdquo; <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/benjamin/1940/history.htm">https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/benjamin/1940/history.htm</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>This is often how it feels to be a developer, especially when encountering non-developers, and <em>a fortiori</em> when doing so developing standards for the future. Where others see a chain of events which is only logical to maintain, we see the piling catastrophe which we cannot truly flee but only ride ahead of in terror.</p>

<h3>We&rsquo;re No Angels</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever heard a technologist use the word &ldquo;legacy&rdquo; like it&rsquo;s the dirtiest, most offensive slur in any human language, this is why. &ldquo;Legacy&rdquo; is the piling catastrophe behind us. But this storm is blowing from no Paradise, or at least so it seems; it seems to blow from the very gates of Hell.</p>

<p>For those of us who do not feel hurtled forward by the piling on of catastrophe, the past holds a certain allure. We call this <em>nostalgia</em> if we are feeling generous; less generously, &ldquo;Are you from the past?&rdquo;  (please watch the whole clip)&hellip;</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/-E4fm4Wqego" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Benjamin wrote of this desire for the past, as well. In <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/ge/benjamin.htm">&ldquo;The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction&rdquo;</a> Benjamin spoke of the loss of the &ldquo;aura&rdquo;, that experience of seeing something human in a made thing. But as is often misunderstood in this piece, Benjamin writes an <em>elegy</em> for the aura. He does not demand that we reclaim the aura, but rather warns against it.</p>

<p>The acceptance of loss is one of the marks of adulthood. The attempt to reclaim the aura is the adolescent revolt against the inevitability of technological society. And like most adolescent revolt, it is both fruitless and deleterious. Acceptance is the final stage of grief, as no rage will resurrect a dead parent, and the revenant will never be that which we once buried.</p>

<h3>And Technology</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s not so different. I&rsquo;m working on a couple of standards groups with members who seem to be mourning a fallen comrade, lamenting a moribund spouse. The only way is forward; we have no choice. That which existed before was of its time, and now we move forward, face turned toward the piling catastrophe of the past. For as much as we might once have loved it, we are driven forward by the wind of its piling wreckage, and can retrieve nothing,</p>

<h3>Paradox</h3>

<p>As I write this essay on technology and Benjamin, I am reminded of another quote, the technologist&rsquo;s paradox and curse.</p>

<p>For there was another, more cynical visionary, of about the same time, F. Scott Fitzgerald, and I am reminded of the ending lines of <em>The Great Gatsby</em></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Gatsby believed in the green light, the orgastic future that year by year recedes before us. It eluded us then, but that’s no matter—tomorrow we will run faster, stretch out our arms farther&hellip; . And then one fine morning—<br/>So we beat on, boats against the current, borne back ceaselessly into the past.</p><footer><strong>F. Scott Fitzgerald</strong> <cite>&ldquo;The Great Gatsby&rdquo;</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>Borne back ceaselessly into the past</h3>

<p>Always. That&rsquo;s how it feels.</p>

<p>Trying to build the future always feels like beating against the current. I think this is why the &ldquo;Angel of History&rdquo; metaphor feels like such a beautiful paradox to me; Blown inevitably forward, yet still having to row against a current pushng backward.</p>

<p>Institutional IT policies, privacy laws, standards bodies&hellip; The fact that people are shocked at the pace of innovation is shocking when you stop to consider the <em>possible</em> pace of innovation.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The future is already here — it&rsquo;s just not very evenly distributed.</p><footer><strong>William Gibson</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Yeah, there was some point to this when I started.</p>

<p>Mostly I was annoyed at what seemed like reactionary elements in my inbox. But I think that&rsquo;s pretty much sorted.</p>

<p>And yet&hellip;</p>

<p>If you are still from the past, know this: there will come a time when your presence is unnecessary. I&rsquo;m still agitating for a Basic Income Guarantee, but I still feel like we&rsquo;re headed toward a tipping point: either some significant percentage of human labor (I&rsquo;d put my money between 70 and 80) will become surplus, or apocalypse.</p>

<p>If we decide traditional free market capitalism is the Best Thing Ever, it&rsquo;ll amount to the same thing, because the 70-80 percent of us rendered redundant will eat one another.</p>

<p>Maybe that&rsquo;s why we have institutionalized incompetent management in the enterprise world (God, please save me from ever returning there). Stifling innovation has a payoff?</p>

<p>Ugh, that&rsquo;s enough weird speculation for tonight.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maybe EdTech Is Another Leaky Abstraction]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/09/30/maybe-edtech-is-another-leaky-abstraction/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T20:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2013/09/30/maybe-edtech-is-another-leaky-abstraction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working in the EdTech sector, I&rsquo;m perpetually vexed as I try to determine what exactly &ldquo;EdTech&rdquo; is and, <em>a fortiori,</em> what <em>effective</em> EdTech should look like. Perhaps a little background might be in order.</p>

<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, my academic training is in philosophy. Computer Science was more of an avocational intellectual pursuit because I enjoyed math and symbolic logic. Life is full of surprises, eh?</p>

<p>One of the fundamental divisions in philosophy is between &ldquo;analytic&rdquo; and &ldquo;continental&rdquo; philosophy. These are vague and overlapping spheres, but the reduction comes down to whether philosophy is the handmaiden of science (analyitc school), or whether philosophy is something larger with a complex (sometimes supportive, sometimes critical) relationship with science.</p>

<p>I fell firmly on the &ldquo;continental&rdquo; side, for the most part. It was always the critical power of philosophy that fascinated me. So, what does this have to do with EdTech?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Technology as the Handmaiden of Education</h3>

<p>This is the problem. Our typical view of &ldquo;educational technology&rdquo; is that we can produce technological tools to support the same tried, tired pedagogical techniques that have (sort of) worked (for a minority of the population) for decades.</p>

<p>This is wasteful. This is stupid, and also wrong.</p>

<p>In business, where technology has succeeded it has done so because it has revolutionized practices, made redundant unnecessary labor, and increased efficiency by many orders of magnitude. I&rsquo;ll (graciously) bracket off my opinions about the unfair distribution of the gains in productivity, for the sake of brevity and focus.</p>

<p>Likewise in science, our rate of accumulation of knowledge about the physical world has increased exponentially, not because we have expected technology to serve the same processes that we accepted as &ldquo;best practices&rdquo; back when we had only stone knives and bear skins to work with, but because the rate of technological progress has disrupted (improved) the very processes by which scientific discovery occurs.</p>

<p>Now, as (to borrow from both Marcuse and Heidegger) technology is very specifically the <em>science</em> of <em>technics,</em>
it might be argues that the sciences are the least &ldquo;disrupted&rdquo; by technological advancement; for the most part, they are themselves advanced. But paradigm shifts in technology have played a role in the Kuhnian paradigm shifts in scientific understanding as well.</p>

<h3>And Education?</h3>

<p>First, let us agree that education is no science, not even a &ldquo;soft science&rdquo; like sociology or psychology. to be sure, at its best it is informed heavily both by those soft sciences as well as slightly harder sciences like cognitive science, for example. But education itself is no science.</p>

<p>In this regard, scientific and technolological advances should in and of themselves present a material critique of the process of pedagogy as it is practiced; technology is the ultimate tool for cultural transformation, if not (ultimately) the transformation of the meaning of what it is to be human.</p>

<p>Fundamentally, when correctly utilized, technology is transformative. And that&rsquo;s not what we&rsquo;re seeing with EdTech.</p>

<p>Smartboards, blended learning, flipped classrooms, Blackboard, Moodle, an iPad for every student, I would go on but you can get better buzzwords from the <a href="http://www.teacheripsum.com/">Teacher Ipsum</a> generator. It&rsquo;s pretty much all a bunch of overpriced junk that supports the Same Old Shit in the classroom, with the added benefit of shiny tech press for the school, the district, whatever.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not playing down the role of technology in education. Quite the opposite, in fact. I&rsquo;m lamenting that billions of dollars are being spent on &ldquo;EdTech&rdquo; that isn&rsquo;t impactful, that isn&rsquo;t transformative, that simply lends the sheen of shiny tech to tired pedagogy that should have been retired decades ago.</p>

<h3>What Is To Be Done?</h3>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>

<p>In the title, I suggested that &ldquo;EdTech&rdquo; is a &ldquo;leaky abstraction.&rdquo; The term comes from an article by <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/AboutMe.html" title="Joel Spolsky">Joel Spolsky</a> entitled <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/LeakyAbstractions.html" title="Leaky Abstractions">&ldquo;The Law Of Leaky Abstractions&rdquo;</a>. The tl;dr is: all (non-trivial) abstractions are, to some degree, leaky; that is, they build on top of something concrete and messy while removing the messy details from the public interface. At least, that&rsquo;s how we&rsquo;d describe it in the software world. Grasping to define something like &ldquo;EdTech&rdquo;, I think the parallel I&rsquo;d like to draw is that the very term &ldquo;EdTech&rdquo; contains what it cannot possibly contain (bonus points if you catch that reference). &ldquo;Educational Technology&rdquo; refers to technology <em>designed for</em> education, technology <em>used in the serivce of</em> education, and also technology tangentially related to education. Unfortunately, this is a boolean <code>and</code>, leaving us with the union of >= 3 overlapping sets, wherein the intersections and complements are probably more interesting. The union of the sets contains many subsets that really aren&rsquo;t all that useful or interesting. But we don&rsquo;t seem to be doing much winnowing.</p>

<p>Back to the philosophy lesson: technology is not there to be the handmaiden of tried and tired pedagogy. Technology is there to, in its very essence, provide an <em>explicit critique</em> of pedagogy in general.</p>

<p>So how do we fix this?</p>

<p>We need better ways of evaluating technology in education. We need professional development solutions to ensure that educators have the skills to properly exploit the tech they have available. We need to ditch our preconceptions about what it means to teach any given subject and look at how technology has changed that domain in the real world (technophobic math teachers, I&rsquo;m looking at you!).</p>

<p>We need to forget everything we know about education, and reinvent everything with the new tools at hand.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
