<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: fiction | Practical Elegance]]></title>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/categories/fiction/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://decomplecting.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-29T02:29:35-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://decomplecting.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lewis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scream When You Learn]]></title>
    <link href="http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/03/11/scream-when-you-learn/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T22:39:38-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://decomplecting.org/blog/2014/03/11/scream-when-you-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Apologies to Charles Bukowski</em></p>

<h4>1.</h4>

<p>I fucking hate this school. All the teachers too. Well, there are a few exceptions, but few enough it doesn&rsquo;t really matter.</p>

<p>There are a few saving graces. Molly, that redhead in fourth period I&rsquo;m dying to fuck. There&rsquo;s a party Friday, maybe that&rsquo;ll happen. At least I&rsquo;ll be drunk enough not to care about this shithole for a few hours.</p>

<p>Had a test today. Fucking Mr. Blum walked over to my desk and watched me solve quadratic equations. Grabbed the calculator out of my hand when he saw me using the program I wrote to solve them. Old fucking moron doesn&rsquo;t even know what these piece of shit TI-83&rsquo;s are capable of. Thought I was cheating.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Writing that goddamn program while I was halfway into the Ballmer Peak was how I learned to <em>understand</em> this irrelevant cocksucking formula, how can he not get that? I don&rsquo;t get these ancient techno-illiterate cunts they put in charge of managing the prison sentence of our youths.</p>

<h4>2.</h4>

<p>They gave us all iPads today. It was exciting until we realized they locked the fuckers down so they could only access Pearson-supplied, school-board-blessed, castrated useless pointless fucking content that isn&rsquo;t going to help me get in Molly&rsquo;s pants, much less learn anything better than I could from an ancient goddamn textbook. Fuck this place. I need a drink.</p>

<p>At least it&rsquo;s Friday. I can get drunk at Pete&rsquo;s place tonight and maybe cop a feel off Molly. At least I can look back on that since this shit school is never going to do a thing to get <em>me</em> into Harvard. Not that that degree would be worth wiping my ass with by the time I would graduate.</p>

<p>Fuck, I might as well devote my time to whiskey and women and poetry, it worked out well enough for that old misogynist bastard Bukowski I read last semester.</p>

<p>At least that fucker was honest, unlike the goddamn assholes handing us crippled iPads.</p>

<h4>3.</h4>

<p>The party was okay. Grabbed Molly&rsquo;s tit for a hot second, she smacked me. Okay.</p>

<p>Pete and Jimmy and I bypassed the shit security on those iPads. Managed to at least get on Facebook and share that stupid quadratic equation solver I wrote for my calculator, not that the other asswipe math teachers like Blum will ever understand the value of writing shit like that. Pretty sure we&rsquo;re getting suspended if not expelled.</p>

<p>I should give up now. What&rsquo;s the fucking point of even trying when the inmates are running the asylum? These fuckers couldn&rsquo;t teach a baby to shit and that&rsquo;s the truth. Why give us iPads when our damn teachers are like a million chimps banging on a million typewriters?</p>

<p>Why didn&rsquo;t somebody teach the fucking teachers?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to fucking scream.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
